

□ (+45) 60 90 60 12 | 🗷 erik@i-solution.de | R⁶ Erik Kusch | 💿 0000-0002-4984-7646 | 🌴 www.erikkusch.com | 🖫 Erik Kusch | 💆 KuschErik

Research Profile

I am a macroecologist specialised in streamlining work-flows, integration, and analysis of big data. My research uses quantitative tools to study ecosystem resilience, vegetation dynamics, and patterns of landscape-scale biodiversity to understand past, present, and future trajectories of ecosystems. My current work includes inference and analysis of ecological networks, simulation-based frameworks for ecological network inference assessments, and software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation.

Education

PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity

01/2020 - PRESENT

(expected graduation: 01/2023)

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

Dissertation: Resilience Of Ecological Networks In The Age Of Extinctions

M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

University of Bergen (UiB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

Thesis: Inferring Vegetation Memory From Remote Sensing Data And Identifying Causal Links To Plant Function

B.Sc. in Biology 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

Specialised Training

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course

Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats

26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics

Glasgow, Scotland 06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities with the R-package Hmsc

Helsinki, Finland

University of Helsinki

02/11/2020 - 06/11/2020

Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems

Hamburg, Germany

University of Hamburg

University of Glasgow

23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

Experience

Research Fellow

Research Station Co-Manager

Scoraig, Scotland

Spatial and Population Ecology, University of Glasgow

06/2019 - PRESENT

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

Bergen, Norway 09/2019 - 12/2019

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide

Saxony, Germany

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS

04/2016 - 06/2016

Research and Teaching Assistant

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG

08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO

05/2017 - 07/2017

07/2018

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP

Student Assistant

BOTANICAL INSTITUTE, TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD)
ZOOLOGICAL COLLECTION, TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD)

05/2016 - 08/2016; 02/2015 - 08/2015

04/2016 - 05/2016; 11/2013 - 08/2015

Teaching & Supervision Activity _____

All Bours Church Curry	3 D
AU Bayes Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	♦ Official Course Web Page
Excursions into Biostatistics Author & Lecturer	Course Web Page
	☐ GitHub Repository
An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R	Course Web Page
AUTHOR & LECTURER	☐ GitHub Repository
Biological Research in Theory and Praxis (BFTP)	② Course Web Page
Author	Aarhus University
Teaching Assistant	Aarhus University
APPLIED STATISTICS	22/03/2021 - 14/05/2021
STATISTICAL AND GEOSPATIAL MODELLING	03/09/2020 - 18/12/2020
GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS	27/10/2020 - 18/12/2020
Instructor & Advisor	
ECOINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS), AARHUS UNIVERSITY	03/02/2021 - 05/05/2021
CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN	08/2017 - 07/2018
Talks & Workshops	
Climate Data with the KrigR Pipeline Workshop	Aarhus, Denmark
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, 5TH CONFERENCE OF NORDIC SOCIETY OIKOS 2022	07/07/2022
Ecological Network Inference - Pipedream or Pipeline	Oxford, England
Invited Speaker, Salgo Team, University of Oxford	22/05/2022
KrigR - The R Package	Hamburg, Germany
Speaker, AK Klima Interimstreffen	25/03/2021
KrigR - Downscaling State-of-the-Art Climate Data for Macroecologists	Aarhus, Denmark
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, BIOCHANGE METHODS WORKSHOPS	12/11/2020
KrigR - Climate Data For Your Spatial Study	12, 11, 2020
Invited Speaker, Salgo Team, University of Oxford	18/06/2020
SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020	25/06/2020
Identifying Ecological-Memory Patterns in Drylands using Remote Sensing	23/00/2020
Invited speaker, Ecosystem Research Group, University of Oxford	15/10/2010
SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR ECOLOGICAL MODELLING CONFERENCE 2019	15/10/2019 04/10/2019
Invited speaker, Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity Research Group, University of Aarhus	06/09/2019
Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance	Bergen, Norway
Invited speaker, BIO Day, University of Bergen	15/03/2019
Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data	Glasgow, Scotlana
Invited speaker, Spatial Ecology Group, University of Glasgow	09/01/2019
Posters	
KrigR — Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data	London, England
POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, BES CLIMATE SCIENCE FOR ECOLOGICAL FORECASTING SYMPOSIUM 2022	11/05/2022
Intrinsic vegetation memory as a proxy of engineering resilience may be an	11/00/2022
oversimplification	
POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020	25/06/2020
Poster author and presenter, International Society for Ecological Modelling Conference 2019	03/10/2019
Poster author and presenter, Bjerknes Centre for Climate Research Annual Meeting 2019	16/09/2019

Extracurricular Activity

Group Member

STATISTICS JOURNAL CLUB, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW	10/03/2021 - PRESENT
Spatial Shared-Interest Group, University of Glasgow	10/03/2021 - PRESENT
Bayes Study Group, University of Bergen	09/2018 - 12/2019
EECRG Reading Group, University of Bergen	10/2017 - 12/2019

Leader & Dungeon Master Aarhus, Denmark AARHUS UNIVERSITY SECTION FOR ECOINFORMATICS DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP 03/2022 - PRESENT

Elected Member: Students Council of Biology Studies at the TUD

Dresden, Germany TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF DRESDEN 10/2013 - 10/2015

Writing

A novel trophic cascade between cougars and feral donkeys shapes desert wetlands

 ${\sf Erick\ Lundgren,\ Daniel\ Ramp,\ Owen\ Middleton,\ Eamonn\ Wooster,\ \textbf{\textit{Erik}\ Kusch},\ [...],\ Arian\ Wallach}$

MOSAIC: A Unified Trait Database to Complement Structured Population Models

Connor Bernard, Gabriel Silva Santos, [...], **Erik Kusch**, [...], Roberto Salguero-Gómez

Rx Preprint - 2022

Vegetation memory effects and their association with vegetation resilience in global drylands

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY, ALISTAIR SEDDON

ᡂ Journal of Ecology - 2022

KrigR - A Tool for Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2022

Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR

RICHARD DAVY, ERIK KUSCH

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2021

Honours & Grants & Awards

SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS

Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship	Aarhus, Denmark
Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norway
Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norway
Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norway
Scholarship , German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes)	Bonn, Germany
	Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond

AWARDS

10/2019	Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher , International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria
10/2019	Modeller's Choice Poster Award, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria